this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet se radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software your code is powerful and so
are you and when you consider the reach
of your code it's clear that to deliver
quality code you must also deliver
secure code where can you start a first
step is educating yourself on basic
secure coding principles and beginning
to put these principles into practice
every day very codes secure coding
toolkit is your go-to resource for all
your secure coding needs the benefits of
our toolkit include learning best
practices for secure coding
understanding how to secure your DevOps
environments learning to combat the most
common software vulnerabilities stay
secure and download this valuable asset
today ww-where code comm / SC radio this
is Robert blumen editor of software
engineering radio if you're hearing this
that means you're a listener of the show
but have you ever thought about being a
host it's a great way to talk to some of
the most interesting people in the
industry and get 30 to 40 thousand
people to hear your thoughts
contact us team @ SC - radio net for
more information
hi this is Jeremy Jung for a software
engineering radio today I'll be speaking
with Aaron Patterson Aaron is on both
the Ruby and rails core teams and
currently works at github Aaron welcome
to software engineering radio oh thank
you first for people who aren't familiar
with Ruby why should they check it out
what's good about Ruby well there's a
lot of good things about Ruby the reason
I really enjoy Ruby is it's just super
fun to program it with like it's a
really enjoyable language to use but I
think part of the reason it's a joy to
use is essentially the consistency of
the language so in Ruby everything is an
object you can contrast that with say
Java for example that has primitive
has objects but also primitive types
whereas in Ruby everything is an object
so you only have to think about that one
like the the mental overhead is a little
bit lower right so I don't know that's
why I enjoy programming with Ruby it's
just it's easy to understand so it's
easy to understand and fun to use
I see so instead of having primitive
types like Java such as boolean and
floats that have different rules than
normal objects everything in Ruby is
treated the same so you can call the
same base methods yep you can call
methods yes everything and it's and it's
really everything like classes or
objects modules or objects everything's
an object so it's like it's just really
I think that consistency like I said it
helps it helps to like lower the mental
overhead of using the language so you
know what to expect you're like what is
this thing you figure out what it is
okay now I can just call methods on it I
mean I think that's one of the things
that sort of I think strikes a lot of
people when they start I guess
specifically with rails which is the web
framework for Ruby mm-hmm there's the
example of being able to use like a
number like say five and then be able to
do doc days yes yeah kind of the
canonical example if you have a saying
like seemed angling like cool how does
that work right yeah
so I guess that's basically because five
is a object and you're able to you can
add methods to it yeah yeah so the
numbers have classes and I mean the
number five is just an instance of an
instance of a I think numeric is a class
and you can just one one thing you can
do in Ruby that's I think unique to the
languages that you can just add and
methods to classes if you want to right
I guess it's a good and bad thing you
can just add you like you can add
methods to any classes you want to so if
you you know that people can abuse that
so don't abuse it but yeah that's it's a
good example so you can just add like
date the method days to the note to the
numeric class and then be like five days
so I think one of the like one of the
other defining characteristics of Ruby
programming is the ability to do better
programming which is essentially just
programs that
programs that write programs right so
you could kind of think of it as I guess
it's like code generation basically you
you write a program that will generate
code and it evaluates it and that's how
you get a lot of the stuff in rails like
for example in your active record models
when you say like has many whatever
you're setting up that relationship it's
actually a meta programmed method active
record being the object relational
mapper for rails for rails yes yes and
you're saying behind that single line of
code there's actually a ton of code
being generated yes yes and that
actually a more simple example is that's
not rail specific is if you write a if
you write a class and you want to add
getter and setter methods to the class
you just do like adder access or foo and
that adds getter and setter methods for
you and it's under the hood it's really
just doing meta program it meta
programming it's defining a method that
returns the value and then it's defining
another method that lets you set set the
value in Java for example if you have a
class you create like that for a person
you could have like a set name and again
name you have to write those functions
yes but in Ruby if you had a person
class at the top of the class you could
write adder accessor and that would
generate methods on the person class or
you get where you set the name yep
exactly yeah cool next I want to talk
about a little bit about how Ruby is
interpreted so what does it mean for a
language to be interpreted versus
compiled so ruby won eight ruby won
eight well before Ruby won nine be was
an interpreted language and essentially
what that means is that it would parse
your code and it would turn the code
into an ast before Ruby 191 ast which is
essentially a tree data structure and
then it would the interpreter would walk
the tree data structure executing each
well whatever was at that node in the
tree would execute that particular
command so if you had a plus node it
would add the you know it would add the
leaves or the child notes at the plus
node so and it would just do this for
the entire parse tree of your of your
program and then in
one nine it change ruby got a virtual
machine and the main difference there is
that the ruby program is compiled into
byte code and then the virtual machine
executes the byte code rather than
walking walking a tree data structure
and then so when you say we got a
virtual machine so does that mean that
the interpreter we had before is not
considered I mean I guess you could call
it a virtual machine in that it's
interpreting a tree but I think that I
think the difference is that you the
interpreter is in or before one nine
that particular style is essentially
walking a tree in and interpreting
whatever instruction is at that point in
the tree whereas the virtual machine is
really trying to model an actual machine
like it's a stack-based
machine so you generate instructions and
then this machine execute the
instructions for as you would like you
know your C compiler generates
instructions for your CPU something more
similar to that so the distinction I
guess when you call something a virtual
machine is that it's running commands
sequentially and there's a I guess a
stack yes is pulling each instruction
from yeah yeah yes
whereas if it's from a tree or it's
parsing a tree then we don't call that a
virtual machine I guess I guess not
yeah I mean it's not written it's not
real it's virtual so what language was
the Ruby interpreter it's written in C
okay yeah so the interpreter is written
in C and also the virtual machine is is
also written in C as well yeah okay
why is C a good language for function I
think that's an that's an interesting
question to ask I don't know if it's
good or not but you can do you can do
tricks with C that you can't do with
other languages or would be difficult to
do with other other languages so for
example one of the techniques that the
virtual machine uses as a technique
called direct threading okay
where it essentially emits jump
instructions rather than typically what
you would do in a virtual machine is you
have a loop that pops instructions off
and they have a sack yeah and then read
well just goes through your your
instruction sequences looking at the
instruction sequence looking that
instruction up in a table and then
jumping to the appropriate function for
that okay whereas with a direct
threading technique you essentially
eliminate that jump table and insert
these jump instructions like you know
the offset of the function that you
actually want to go to so rather than
doing the look up in a table you omit a
jump instruction to say go and I mean a
machine jump instruction not a not a
Ruby VM jump instruction you say go to
this address and execute execute the
code there and that type of trick is
something that you can do and see that
maybe you can't do and you can't do in
other languages it it may be possible
but it's a common trick and see so you
said like you would normally have this
lookup table that tells you is that
where in memory - is that like in the
stackers in the heap it's gonna be well
that that lookup table is gonna be in
the heap and essentially what it is is
just the key is the key is the
instruction like say the instruction for
the virtual machines say you have like a
push instruction or something and it
looks that up in the in the table and
then it says okay well here's the
function pointer to execute the execute
the push instruction and then it goes
and executes that whereas using this
direct threading technique you can
eliminate that lookup essentially so
like you're going through a list of
instructions I guess and you get to some
kind of I guess machine level
instruction you need to execute yes and
instead of looking at a lookup table in
the heap you would have like an awesome
memory offset just I guess would that be
in the stack or yes okay and then you'd
say go there okay so right from the
stack you would say like okay go to this
position from where you are yeah and you
don't need to do the lookup you don't
need to do the load exact
okay and we're gonna say something oh
the just that those types of like memory
techniques are things that you can do
like that's a thing you can do and see
where I'm I don't think you could do
that in Java for example maybe you could
do it in rust what I doubt it would be
safe considered safe right so those
types of unsafe tricks are things you
can do and see but those those are kind
of I guess the reasons why you would use
C but at the same time that's also why
you're saying C might be its danger
Dangerous yeah so it's kind of like you
know it's a really powerful tool and
that's why everyone chooses to use it
but it's a double-edged sword yes yes
but it's I mean and then the downsides
of course are that C is not a very
friendly language yeah especially
considered you know compared to like
Ruby or Python or other scripts yeah
yeah it's not like C's
C C does not spark joy you were saying
though that like you know is C a good
language for VM and you know you're kind
of like well it is and maybe it isn't
you know it are there any you know
alternatives like the realistic
alternatives or wow that's a really good
question I have not thought of it I have
not thought of an answer to that I would
say like from my perspective the two two
things come to the top of my head first
would be first would be rust the second
would actually be scheme okay
specifically my favorite my favorite
scheme which is chicken scheme but
chicken scheme essentially compiles down
to C okay but at least you can at least
you can write and scheme and not in C so
there's that so so is it is it writing
the scheme code is a safer environment
or what what I guess what why would you
say that well it's I mean writing it
writing the scheme code I guess I don't
know if you could do the
that directs reading technique that I
was talking about I don't know if you
could do that in pure just plain old
scheme scheme is a lot nicer to write
than see is and I think rust is also a
lot nicer to write than see is so
basically when I think about it I think
about you know developer ergonomics like
how hard is the language to use
basically what do you think is like the
main thing blocking say rust from
becoming a language that you could write
vmz honestly I don't think that there is
anything blocking it necessarily I am
quite sure people are writing virtual
machines as rust now yeah I actually I
know there is a one for Python yeah a
couple of people are working on outside
of that yeah I mean I guess right now
it's a bunch of sort of toy projects you
know where people are trying to figure
out like what is the limits of rust and
hopefully you know they'll find out like
hey maybe maybe this is something we
could use in place of C or maybe we
still have a ways to go yeah so I think
I mean I don't I personally don't think
there's any blockers necessarily because
I think that those those toy projects
will eventually turn into real things so
mainly the the blocker that I and I'm
doing air quotes for your listener here
listeners here the the main blocker I
think is just popularity like getting
more like getting more people to use it
so right that's that's the only thing
so just adoption yeah exactly yeah I
mean it'll be yeah it'll be interesting
to see like you know in a few years if
maybe when somebody's thinking of making
a new language maybe they do look to
rust before they look to see yeah yeah
tonight I personally would yeah if you
were writing Aaron's Ruby VM or
something that really goes rust
okay yeah okay I think mainly I'd say
probably the reason Ruby is written in C
is essentially just legacy like it's
been around for 25 years
rust is not around that long yeah yeah
yeah I mean who knows maybe if you know
Maps the creative Ruby maybe if he was
making it and rust was around maybe
would have chosen it yes
yeah yeah it could be and I think one
thing I one thing actually I know we're
talking about Ruby today but one thing I
like about rust that I think is cool is
you can like so you can write stuff in
rust and you can export symbols to see
from Russ okay so it seems possible that
like for example I could rewrite Ruby's
garbage collector in rust but still be
able to embed it within a C C project as
long as I export it C project such as
Ruby as long as I exported the right
symbols so I think that's one thing
that's exciting about that language and
for those who aren't familiar with C
when you're exporting a symbol like what
is that that mean in the context of C it
just means that your C program knows or
the linker knows where the function
offsets are so you can link against it
and say like when you compile your C
program you're like I had there's a
function in this shared library and I
want to call that function and it's able
to link and look it up okay so you could
be in your C program like there because
Ruby the Ruby VM is written in C yeah
and like you were saying you could have
calls to a garbage collector that's
written in rust and you could call those
directly from C yes okay and it would
have access to the actual like exact
memory locations of those calls yes okay
yeah got it
so starting with Ruby one nine you said
you you introduced her coochie yeah
Chloe T you wrote a virtual machine yep
and introduced that Koichi when he
decided to create the the VM was there a
specific reason was it like performance
or what was the primary motivator I mean
the main thing was for performance but I
know he also did it for his PhD thesis
okay yeah so that was probably another
motivating like motivating factor but I
mean really performance how much like
how much of a difference are we are we
talking I guess between you know the
interpreter versus the compilation at VM
I to be honest I don't know a lot it's
yes it's like it's very much faster okay
that's a good metric yeah
an exact number but I sure if you're
very fast okay okay so like after you
know after he had done in people saw
there was also like wow this was this
was definitely worth it yes okay okay
why why is it so much faster than
interpreting like going through the ast
versus just going from the Ruby code to
the instruction sequences like why is
that faster it's actually kind of
interesting
Ruby's compiler still has to produce an
AST mhm and then it essentially takes
that ast then walks the ast and
translate it translates it into bytecode
which the virtual machine executes right
what's kind of funny is that Ruby 1/8
the interpreted version had to do the
same thing except that it just stopped
at the step where it came up with the
the tree so you'd produce the ast and
then it would walk the ast and interpret
it whereas it's kind of counterintuitive
but the the compiled version with the
virtual machine actually has to do more
work mm-hmm it has to produce the
bytecode
right but you can actually like once it
produces this bytecode you can actually
apply some optimizations to the bytecode
so you can do like some dead code
analysis peephole optimizations there's
different types of optimizations that
you can apply to this style of code that
you couldn't apply to just a tree and I
think on top of that there's also other
things like I don't know how I don't
know how big a factor this is but a
virtual machine executing bytecode is
gonna be more friendly for CPU caches
than a doing an AST interpreter and it's
the interpreter because you have like
memory all over the place so I'm not
sure what percentage that plays into the
or what percentage that factors into it
but it's there so there's various
different factors that make a virtual
machine faster just because like the
nature of sequential instructions is
kind of a very well-known problem I
guess and people have come up with all
sorts of ways to
yeah absolutely yeah okay yeah so we can
take those basically take those
instructions and then apply known like
known common optimizations for those to
the Ruby code and then this virtual
machine that we're referring to believe
it's referred to as yet another Ruby
p.m. yes yeah okay and this was also
written in C yes yeah yes okay one thing
I found sort of interesting is before I
was actually chewing research for this
interview you know I was thought of Ruby
as an interpreted language right like I
always thought like okay you you write
your Ruby code and then the interpreter
is reading your code and as it reads the
code you know through the ast you know
things are executing on the machine but
this is more like it seems a little bit
more like Java if I'm not wrong we're
with Java right you write your Java code
you use a compiler to compile it down to
JavaScript
a space and you have like you know your
program alright so why is there not like
the same sort of bytecode compilation
step it does it does have the bytecode
compilation step it does all the same
steps but it never generates the
intermediary file so it does take care
it takes your program and it does
convert it into bytecode it's just that
it keeps a bytecode in memory and then
immediately executes it so you there's
there's actually an interface where you
can say compile a file and actually
produce a produce an intermedia file if
you want to it's just that people don't
really do it do you know if there is any
specific reason why like with Ruby you
don't tend to do that but with other
languages you do I think because well I
would say it's because Ruby's
origins are just a scripting language
you just you just run it right so nobody
wanted to add that extra step like you
just want to run your code yeah yeah
so I'd guess that's the reason and I
guess like that isn't stopping like
startup time we're making it like too
long or anything well actually that's
that's an interesting question because
it does it does slow startup time okay
like I think that's an interesting an
interesting issue with this set up so
previously we were talking about Ruby
1:8 having to go through essentially the
same steps as Ruby 1:9 but Ruby one
nine-halves to do more because it's
converting it to bytecode and then
executing the bytecode which means that
the virtual machine has to be fast
enough to make up for the extra work
that it's okay right right
so that parse and compile time it is
overhead that's being added to your
program so actually if somebody made a
gem called boot snap that what it does
is you add this gem to your rails
application and it will it will compile
all of your Ruby code into intermediate
files like we were talking about and
then when you boot your application
rather than evaluating the the text RB
files it'll actually load those load
those binary files and we found that it
takes off maybe what was it I don't
remember exactly it's like 20 percent or
something like that overhead okay so 20%
reduced reduction in the start time yes
yes yes okay so that's like that's
something that's specific to Rails stuff
no no no this is I mean you could use
this like they designed it such to be as
to be put in with a rails application
but this technique you could use you
could use with any library that you
wanted to interesting yeah so it's like
in a way people didn't do it because it
didn't seem like a problem yeah and then
I guess startup times maybe specifically
with rails were a little high yeah yeah
I mean typically like a typical rails
application is going to have a way more
code
you know just some script that you're
writing right right so in those cases
where you have a large amount of code
that that time does actually make a
difference so that's a case where you'd
want to use it cool yeah so another
thing I want to talk about is we've been
talking about how you take the Ruby code
converted to an ast compile it down to
what was the sort of bytecode called or
there's no is no name so the bytecode
gets run by the VM so this is a little
different than like say C right because
C you write your code and it actually
compiles down to machine code yeah why
would a language choose to compile to
virtual machine instructions versus
directly to machine code so so usually
usually you compile down to like this
this is the promise of the java virtual
yeah i'll down to basically a common
bytecode way you could run on any like
you could take it anywhere so you take
your class files make your jar file and
you can run it on any machine as long as
you have a java vm right so that's i
think that's like the main so I guess
portability is one of the main main
selling points of compiling the bytecode
which rubies I think one of the things
is that Ruby's the the bytecode that I
told you about that you can generate it
is not portable okay so the dream came
real for a job yes but okay yes yes like
for example if you have a it's the
bytecode that you dump if you dump it in
Ruby on a little endian machine it won't
work on a big endian machine oh really
yes it's not the Indian this is like you
can't do it you got to run it on the
same if you're gonna do that you need to
run it on the same architecture which I
mean we use this technique turns out in
practice it's like fine
like I'm not running you know know what
nobody is doing this nobody is running
and I'm like nobody is developing on
little-endian and then pushing pushing
too big
in production plus I guess like you said
the people typically don't do
precompilation - you know the the
bytecode and then copy it to another
machine right so no it doesn't actually
end up being an issue I guess in that
yeah it practice it's not actually a
problem but we do like the main
advantages of turning it into a bytecode
for for Ruby or essentially the
optimizations versus during the
interpretation yes right yeah okay but
versus compilation to machine code for
compilation to machine code it's better
like I mean if you could compile it to
me
compiled completely to machine code that
might run that might actually execute
faster but I guess the idea is that we
have some things that are specific to
our like our language that it would be
nice if a chip implemented this
instruction that would be great but we
want to have more complex instructions
and what chip supports the other the
other thing is that in this case like
our VM is a stack based VM rather than a
register based one which is different
than machines like actual machines
actually work so there's that issue -
can you like kind of briefly explain
what the difference is between like a
stack based and the register base yeah
so the stack based stack based one
basically each instruction pushes and
pops off of a off of a stack so you'd
say like for example if you do the add
and if you want to add two numbers you
would push the two numbers onto a stack
so you'd have three instructions you'd
say push one push two and then you would
add and then add would pop the two off
and and push the new value on similar to
an HP calculator okay or an RPN you know
reverse polish notation calculator if
anybody out there uses those which I did
in school whereas whereas a register
based machine is where you'd say like
okay I'm going to read and write from
particular registers so you'd say like
I'm going to put this number in one
register put this other number and I
differ
register and then I'm going to call the
ad like the add instruction which reads
out of those and then puts into it puts
the results into a different register so
there-there is no concept of the stack
right you're mutating you're mutating
registers rather than like pushing and
popping off oh okay so you're you're fit
you have to think about the actual
position of everything yeah where's with
the stack like it's just kind of kind of
throw and drink and you don't have to
worry about like where on the machine
yes that stack is stored yeah okay so
that's one difference is that the route
since Ruby's VM is a stack-based one
which is different from an actual
machine we can't do that stuff okay
interesting another thing I wanted to
talk about is Ruby has I believe there's
two separate API there's a core API and
a standard library mmm is that right
yeah what's the distinction between the
two the main distinction is that the
core or the standard library you have to
require it like you have to specifically
say like I'm gonna use this whereas the
core stuff is just you don't need to
require anything it's just immediately
available okay okay so this standard you
have to manually add it in yep even
though it is shipped shipped with Roo
yeah it's shipped with Ruby but you have
to opt into those functions basically
yeah
one thing I've also kind of wondered is
how much of the core API in the standard
library are written in Ruby and how much
of it is C I'd say like core is probably
99% C and the standard library is
probably I would say I'm just estimating
here maybe like 80 percent Ruby oh okay
so the standard library stuff is mostly
just Ruby code that you can load and use
whereas the chorus F is just mainly C
components okay and the core library
that would be like really foundational
stuff like strings rings dates numbers
yeah okay okay and then things like say
the JSON parser I'm gonna be in this
ok and then so if somebody wanted to
contribute to Ruby and the only new ruby
like then it's actually possible for
them to look at the standard library yes
that's correct
okay interesting very cool you're on
both the Ruby and the rails core teams
yes do you program more in C or more in
Ruby when you're doing that that kind of
work it's a good question lately I've
been doing more C programming it really
just depends on what I what I need to
work on at the time like lately since
I've been doing work on the garbage
collector that's all C C code whereas
like when I want to do peer railsconf
I'm going to talk about improving the
performance of templates the template
rendering system and that's all Ruby the
view rails views I'm going to talk about
that and that's all Ruby code okay it
just depends on which parts I'm touching
right your code is powerful and so are
you and when you consider the reach of
your code it's clear that to deliver
quality code you must also deliver
secure code working you start a first
step is educating yourself on basic
secure coding principles and beginning
to put these principles into practice
every day very codes secure coding
toolkit is your go-to resource for all
your secure coding needs the benefits of
our toolkit include learning best
practices for secure coding
understanding how to secure your DevOps
environments learning to combat the most
common software vulnerabilities stay
secure and download this valuable asset
today WWV our code comm /sc radio next
i'd like to talk about something that i
think when a lot of people think of Ruby
and they think of performance whether or
not is justified they think of what's
called the global interpreter lock
mm-hmm so both Ruby and Python and I'm
not sure there's other languages they
have this this global interpreter lock
this Gil yeah could you kind of define
what that is sure in Ruby 1 8 it was a
GI l global global interpreter lock but
now that we have a VM it's a GVL global
via global VM lock so basically what it
does is it
ensures that only one thread is
scheduled on the machine at a time
that's that's all it does so it makes
sure that only one thread can be
scheduled on the machine at a time okay
so you can have multiple threads yes but
only one of them can be being run at any
given time yes exactly okay so what it
means I guess what it means is that
there's actually a lot of nuances here
too because it's possible to unlock that
GPL so you can say like I want to
execute outside of the outside of the
GPL but you have to do that in C so
let's say for example you have some kind
of CPU bound operation that you would
like to execute in parallel so for
example maybe you're calculating up
let's say you're doing a Bitcoin show or
something like that and you have a
library that's written in C and that is
CPU bound so what you would say is in
your in your C extension you say hey I
know this is CPU bound I'm gonna unlock
now let it do its thing and then relock
and then that way the VM can schedule
other threads to execute on the CPU at
the same time and you can do the same
thing for i/o operations as well so as
long as it's whatever operation that
you're doing as long as that operation
doesn't need to call back into the Ruby
virtual machine you can unlock around
that a common example is that all the
i/o operations in Ruby so if you say
like file dot read or socket dot right
or whatever those will unlock the global
or the GPL and they'll that'll allow you
to do things in parallel so you could
say like you could create a thousand
threads and write to a thousand sockets
okay okay so the the gvl the this is why
I say there's nuance to this thing
the GPL schedules one thread on the CPU
at a time for pure Ruby code prepared
okay just for a ravika
yes okay yes so anything that's written
in C you have the possibility to unlock
it mm-hmm and you were just talking
about how there are portions of say like
the core API that are written and C
is that considered like a part of that C
code that can run in parallel or yes
okay yeah okay yeah so we can say like
in the in the C code the implementation
for the write function it'll say like
unlock we know this is an i/o bound
operation that does not need to call
into the VM so unlock now do the under I
underlying right call and then relock
the VM so during that time when you're
actually writing to the socket or
whatever the VM can schedule another
thread on the on the CPU to do something
in parallel if I'm getting or making web
requests for example like I could make
you know 100 at the same time because
it's actually the C code that is doing
that work they can all run
simultaneously yeah okay and then you
were saying like if you wanted to run
things in parallel yourself that could
be done through a C extension yeah you
typically if you want to run things
truly in parallel you have to do it
through C extension or use a C extension
that that knows how to unlock and relock
the GVL correctly so you you can have
parallel as I'm just not using Ruby cut
your Ruby code yes yes so you cannot run
pure Ruby code in parallel got it if you
remove the Gil what what breaks tons of
stuff one example of stuff that breaks
is basically all data structures in Ruby
or not thread safe so you could you
could unlock the people have done this
you can just take it out if you want if
you don't schedule any threads
everything will work fine but if you
schedule a thread and like two of those
threads mutate the same hash then you'll
get a seg v or something you'll just get
a segmentation fault okay okay so that's
one benefit of this gvl and that's the
same in I believe this is the same in
Ruby and Python also JavaScript too we
don't have to have locks on those data
structures because since only one thing
can be scheduled at a time you may get
you may get race conditions because it's
it's concurrent right but you don't
seg fees because it's not parallel the
data structures or the implementation of
things in Ruby are not thread safe and I
guess that allows the implementation
maybe to be simpler yes and I guess
you're saying it's also the same way
with Python yeah and so is that the
reason why like say JRuby is able to
remove the kill I believe right yes and
is that because they reimplemented all
of the sort of core API things yeah so
they they implement theirs with um I
don't think that their hash
implementation hash for example but also
array 2 I don't think that those are
thread safe but on the JVM you'll just
get an error saying like oh you have a
you did a parallel updater all right
okay but they do have thread safe data
structures available to you too because
it's built on Java yeah yep so they
actually have a separate class you could
do so you could have like a thread safe
array or sighs okay I mean it so so I
believe JRuby and and MRI will have the
same issue if you try to update one data
structure in parallel it's just that on
JRuby you get a nice exception yeah okay
and on MRI you would get a sec view
range it's not not idea no no no it's
not as well I would rather look at an
exception than it than a hit then a
segue so right and so you're saying
python is probably the same same class
and then I'm not an expert in JavaScript
but I believe you don't have manual
control over threat yeah threads at all
yeah it's like they don't have a deal
you can do i/o operations in parallel
the same as on Ruby right you can do
those things you can do those things in
parallel but since they they have that
they only schedule one one CPU operation
at a time it's functionally the same
thing as having a GDL there is no lock
but you just can't you can't
yeah you can't make you can't make a
thread anyway so make sense
there's a few options for concurrency
within Ruby right mm-hmm
you know there's there's forking right
so you can spawn a new process there's
multi-threading but that has limitations
due to the Gil yeah
and then I guess you have the ability to
do an event loop kind of like JavaScript
or no me right when you're developing in
Ruby like how would a developer choose I
guess what's the best model for them
that's a that is a good question too it
depends on the needs of your system I
think at work we use a forking model as
seems to work like that form of
parallelism seems to work fine for us
but you could also do like you could
just use a threading web server for
example like I think the default one
with rails now is Puma which is a
threading web server and as long as your
operations like as long as your
application is i/o bound you'll get
great parallelism out of the threading
server for example you work at github
right so it's a lot of I guess wet or
HTTP traffic honestly I think a lot of
our stuff is i/o bound well actually
that may not be true anymore I think we
have generating totes so it's it's kind
of hard cuz like doing database stuff is
clearly i/o like you're waiting on i/o
right yeah but when you like actually
generate the HTML to send back down to
the client that's going to be CPU hmm
before you send it and then when you
send it at i/o and that's primarily
written in Ruby yes yeah yeah yeah so we
use we use a forking model but I mean
you can get great results out of a great
results out of a threading model too it
just depends on your application
honestly if I was a new developer or
what I would do is just go with the
defaults I would just use Puma put it in
into production wait to see what kind of
scaling issues I have and then make my
decision based off of that okay so
probably start with threads yeah okay
yeah and then at github
I believe you use unicorn which is a web
server that uses Forks or additional
processes for concurrency so does that
mean let's say like a thousand people
hit the site
is it spawning a process for each hit or
like how's that no we use a pre forking
model that Forks I don't remember how
many processes but it Forks offs like
some some number of processes so we have
a fixed essentially a fixed number of
people that can be using our website
concurrently and if that gets full then
people are essentially put into a queue
and we drain that cute just as an
example you spent up 50 processes and
there's a queue in front of all those
processes and it just passes it to each
okay yeah I've got it
when you use say JavaScript and you want
to do something with concurrency there's
like concurrency primitives that are
built in like for example there are the
concept of promises the async await
keywords in Java and.net they have their
own sort of task or concurrency related
libraries mm-hmm is that something that
you think would ever come to Ruby or its
kind of hard to say because like you
could think of a thread is essentially a
promise sure okay right you could say
like I want you to execute this code and
I don't care when you do it I want to
get the value at a later date and then
you'd ask the thread hey are you done
and when it's actually there's a method
on on thread in Ruby you can say dot
value and that'll actually block alcohol
it it'll block until the thread finish
right remember doing so you could spin
off a thread and let it do whatever I do
I'm not sure what the fundamental
differences between that and a promise
are because both are just saying I want
you to compute this and I will get the
value at a later date yeah I think like
and maybe certain things like being able
to chain calls together yeah for example
you can say in JavaScript I want to run
this HTTP call than this one yeah yeah
and like depending on the result of that
one run this one and it's sort of
written in like a flat structure so you
can kind of yeah you could do it so it's
I think that Ruby has all the primitives
to do something like that just if you
want to have an API like that you have
to use a gem right right right we also
have fibers
which you can think of as essentially
co-routines there's their threads but
you have to implement your own
scheduling model basically so there's
that that too and then of course like
Cochise working on guilds but that's
different than promises so I think I
mean it depends on what you want to
accomplish if you want to accomplish
execute this thing for me mm-hmm
you can do it right and like like you
said there are there are gems or
packages where people have built sort of
these concurrency I guess building
blocks yes um so if you want to use
promises or you want to use something
like a sink a wave like you can it's
just through a gem right region being
yeah in the standard library or than
Horner yep you mentioned fibers I wonder
if we can talk a little bit about that
because at the Ruby conference Ruby kaya
they were talking about a new web server
called Falcon by Samuel Williams that
uses Vipers for concurrency mm-hm and I
wasn't sure how that was different than
using threads or processes yeah to be
honest I need to study how he is doing
that exactly or how that wrote libraries
written exactly because essentially all
fibers are is their co-routines you say
like you run a fiber and inside the
fiber you can say hey I want to switch
off to something else now it's truly
imagine that you had you had threads and
you had to implement your own scheduler
for the threads and that is what fibers
are is like you they're essentially a
thread yeah but you need to say like hey
I want to pass off now I want somebody
else to handle like do something so
where the threads it's that that
scheduling is automatic by the operating
system
yeah whereas these fibers the scheduling
is manual you have to say hey go go do
this other thing and so like you would
be able to say okay go do this other
thing but you have to have some way of
coming back to the fiber right yes yeah
you'd have to so that other thing has to
go back and say like hey I'm done now
you go ahead yeah yeah okay
so you have to manage like you have to
manage that and that's why I think it
sounds like a pain okay not something
you want to think about if you're like
building your app right yeah schedule
schedule that stuff exactly which is why
I say and you just study how this web
server works because honestly it sounds
like a huge pain and the other the other
thing is that when you use when you use
threads with Ruby as I was saying
earlier io operations will unlock the
unlock the GVL which gives the VMO an
opportunity to schedule other threads on
the cpu right right whereas if you're
doing that with a fiber fibers do not
run in parallel and it doesn't know the
scheduler doesn't know hmm okay so you
would have to say like I'm gonna do an
i/o operation I'll switch I'll switch
fibers or like I don't even know how all
right I guess what you're saying is like
with fibers I mean you're doing the
scheduling yourself so you could have
ten sort of concurrent tasks where
you're jumping between them going I'm
gonna do a little bit of this a little
bit of this but they still can't run in
parallel because they never they never
drop-down to see I guess or drop down
into the Ruby runtime to say like hey
this is the you're never running so
you're never running a thread like
there's no thread it's just there's no
threat oh okay yeah so there's no
threads you can that parallel okay
okay got it so I say I need to study it
because I I feel skeptic Rea maybe you
guys can have a conversation yeah next
I'd like to talk about the work being
done to add a just-in-time compiler to
Ruby there's a lot of excitement around
that lately
do you expect a pretty big difference in
performance it's hard to say right now
like if you look at if you run the JIT
against CPU bound programs it works
pretty well
like if you take one of the benchmarks
that we use is we have an nes an nes
emulator yeah
and that's written in Ruby and if you
use the JIT with the nes emulator you
get really good results like it's it's
much faster yeah but if you use the JIT
with a rails application actually
close down the reel so okay although
Coco Bloom the person working on the JIT
he's giving a presentation here at
railsconf so maybe he has some new
numbers but the last time I saw a number
is it like it would actually made your
rails out slow not maybe not what
they're going do it I do have pretty
high hopes so is is there anything
specific about rails you think that
makes it slow with the current
implementation of the JIT I don't know
for sure but I would suspect that it's
due to a lot of the well first off the
number of method calls that we make so
it's this JIT is a method method based
JIT so you need to you need to do some
tweaking to say like how many methods
you want cached
how many methods you want compiled and
rails calls a lot of methods and on top
of that rails also has a lot of
indirection so I think those two factors
may be inhibiting the JIT so when you
refer to indirection is that like a
method calling a method call oh yeah and
so for a JIT I guess it's it's better to
have a like a shorter stack yeah yeah
yeah and I think I mean it may be it may
be fine
it may be okay it's just that I really
think it's the number of methods that
are involved since we're calling so many
methods it's just bad it's bad for the
JIT essentially and I think we another
thing is a lot of the I believe a lot of
the meta programming that we do in rails
some of the things that we do in there I
don't know what specifically but some of
the things we do in there will
invalidate cause and validations in the
JIT so to give an example like when you
say in validation like the JIT is
compiling like certain functions down to
machine code is yes but then rails does
something to the function so for example
let's say you had a let's say you had a
simple method that was like you know 1
plus 2 or something right and that got
cheated cheated out to machine code but
then later on say somebody adds the
day's method to
the number class right now now the
method tables are different the shape of
that date the shape of that type is
different and because of that we have to
invalidate this we have to invalidate
this jittered method so I don't know all
of the things that would do that but I'm
also pretty confident that if there are
things that do that rails does them okay
takes full advantage of the same thing
you told people maybe don't do very cool
is there is there anything else you
wanted to mention or I think we should
have talked about I don't know we can
talk about my GC work okay yeah yeah
that sounds good before we do that let's
maybe just quickly define what GC does
and what its role is yeah sure so G the
GC is for I mean
GC technology is very old it was
invented in the 70s with Lisp and
essentially what it does is manage
memory for you so you don't have to
malloc and free things on your own
it's just managed by this thing called a
garbage collector it just takes care of
that stuff for you and you don't need to
think about it yeah so basically like
rather than in C you know you would have
to allocate memory and you would have to
free the memory when you're done with it
otherwise it would just continue to grow
yeah right
GC sort of just takes care of that for
you yeah and trying to think of we have
time to sort of do a whirlwind tour of
like you know Ruby's GC journeyer we
should just jump to your work I can give
you I can give you an overview of what
the the technology that it currently
uses it's a so like I said I don't know
how into the weeds who want to get here
but rubies rubies garbage collector is
can it's a concurrent garbage collector
so it runs concurrently with the program
it's a generational GC so it use it's a
generational mark-and-sweep
garbage collector that has I'm just
throwing out all the buzzwords
we could we could maybe go a little bit
into so the tamarkan suite for example
right yes that's like finding all the
objects that are not being used being
used and then it's actually pausing the
program right and then doing its work to
figure out what's being used and then
remove the things that are yes exactly
and then you see you mentioned
concurrent GC yes so I guess that's just
they're all happening at the same time
or yeah so what basically what the what
the GC does is we have so it's a it's a
generational it's also a generational
garbage collector but it uses the three
color algorithm look this up later
but basically what this what this
algorithm allows you to use as tricolor
marking is what it's called it's called
tricolor marking and what this algorithm
allows you to do is it allows you to
pause in the middle of the marking step
so you don't need to like yes you had
you have to stop the program to perform
GC but because you can do it
incrementally it means that you pause
for a short amount of time and then you
let the you let the program continue so
you have more frequent pause times but
those pause times are shorter and the
throughput of your the overall
throughput of your program is higher
essentially it's the same concept it's
marking objects and throwing them away
but it can do like a little bit time
yeah so that your application has like a
lot of quick pauses rather than long
time long pauses yeah yeah exactly so
uses a tricolor marking technique so
that it can do that right so it's
generational it's generational - so it
looks at it looks at old objects less
frequently than it looks at new objects
which also speeds up the speeds up the
GC so I can put them into categories
like I can look at an object that is
frequently being used and it can say
like okay I probably don't have to look
at this one for a while because I've
noticed it's getting used constantly
uses age so when it was like if some
object comes to life
and the GC runs say three times and that
object was able to survive three GC is
then it's like look at you look like
maybe we don't need to look at you so
frequently right then the other the
other technique it uses a thing called
lazy sweeping which is essentially the
same a similar technique to the tricolor
marking in that you don't need to halt
the program it can it sweeps it sweeps
objects away incrementally so it'll
pause and sweep in pause and sweep so
essentially the same ideas that you get
short pause times and higher throughput
right okay and then the techniques that
I am working on is a compactor which is
basically for reducing heap
fragmentation so you'll end up with the
garbage collector like because of these
the algorithms that it's using you'll
end up with essentially holes in your
heap where you have you know place where
there's no object anymore and this
compaction the compactor that I have
finished and it's gonna be in Ruby to
seven it essentially allows you to get
rid of the holes and those in the heap
okay so it's like as we're creating a
bunch of objects they're all getting
like put into memory but they're getting
put like all over the place right or
well yeah they're put I mean they're put
like they're all put into a row like the
you keep adding them to a list
essentially but but you know let's say a
GC occurs and some of those ones
previously died and they went away so
now you get holes there so you'll end up
with like you just end up with these
holes in it and you can you can use a
compactor to compress and get rid of
those holes and what that means is the
benefits are essentially more efficient
use of memory it takes a while maybe to
notice that you have all those holes and
fill them in so if we compact it it can
reduce like we say we put all these
long-lived objects together maybe we
don't need to look at those pages as
frequently different we can use
different techniques to basically speed
up the speed up the GC and mutator with
that it's kind of like going back to the
generational concept where you're saying
long-lived objects right you may
don't need to look at you know and you
can keep them all together like during
this compacting yes okay very cool yeah
so that's that's what I've been working
on and I am I am excited about it it is
what I I'm excited about it because I
wrote it it took me like three years to
write the stupid thing I think like
what's what's great about that though is
that when you work on something
it affects all ruby applications right
yes so you know you can you can work
three years in this case and if you get
like let's say a 10% decrease in memory
usage or something like that that is you
know that is across everyone that's
using Ruby is like they're decreased yes
yeah it's it's cool yeah so that's like
that's that's fantastic it's like more
than just oh um you know I'm optimizing
my app and I have made it like I made it
faster you know that's cool but like
you're like I just made 2 million apps
faster yes yes yeah yeah that's awesome
one of the things that motivates me to
work on stuff like that yeah it's like
it's not just not just me and our app in
particular it's like everybody so so
like would you say the primary benefit
with the compaction is it speed is it
reduced memory usage like what's the the
main gain it's hard so it's hard to say
it depends so one one of the things that
we're looking at so weird you have to
say like whenever you're looking at
performance stuff you always have to say
like it depends yeah
if someone doesn't say if someone
doesn't say it depends they're probably
why yeah so in this in this case we use
I mentioned before we use a forking
forking web server and for when you fork
off killed Rijn the children share
memory with the parent process right but
one of the issues is that I'll briefly
explain the copy-on-write
copy and write performance technique is
essentially like you fork off a child
the child process shares memory with the
parent they like it has as far as the
child is concerned it has the same
memory that the parent has right
but that's not actually what's happening
what's happening is the OS is the
operating system basically has a pointer
back to the parents memory okay so if
you have a program that consumes four
megabytes if you fork a child process
you don't suddenly have 8 megabytes you
still have four but you have two
processes so you didn't actually gain
any memory you didn't yeah you were able
to get two processes but you didn't you
didn't double your memory usage however
if the child process rights to the
memory clearly you don't want the parent
process to be written to as well right
right
so what the operating system will do is
it'll say okay if you're writing to this
region of memory I'm gonna copy whatever
memory was in the parent process I'm
gonna actually copy that to you now ok
so you get the child process gets a copy
of that and that's the the copy and
write optimization is so that you can
have two processes that don't consume
twice the memory okay but when you write
to that memory you get a copy so that
it's oh okay so when it when you first
fork a process as long as you're only
reading it's actually reading the memory
from the original process so if I had
like an object like like a string or
something and I read it from the second
process it would actually be reading the
first processes yes string then as soon
as I mutate it then I get my own copy
yep exact cut it yep so that you can
maintain isolation from each other so
where this issue comes into play is that
so let's say you allocate a bunch of
objects and then some of them get GC and
now you've got these holes in your heap
mm-hmm you fork a child yeah now the
child just you're doing something
innocuous like you're allocating an
object but it gets allocated into an an
unused slot and that's a right okay okay
so unfortunately what that means is that
so the the operating system when it
copies memory it doesn't copy just the
memory that you wrote to okay it copies
it has to copy in fixed size okay so on
Linux I think it's 4k
so even though you wrote this maybe tiny
objects you'll end up getting 4k copied
to your child process and you could
possibly get like the object you wanted
and then like pieces of whatever is left
yeah exactly exactly so my idea here is
that if we compact the heap before
forking there will be no there will be
no spaces for you to allocate any
allocate any objects into so now the
child process when it allocates a new
object it'll allocate it off into an
empty like an empty location something
that's not shared right the issue is
that eventually if you're eventually if
you have holes everywhere eventually all
of its going to be copied to the child
process whereas if we don't have any
holes then none of it will be copied to
the child interesting very cool so
that's one that's one thing and there's
some other there's some other
optimizations like it could it's
possible it could increase performance
but with the particular algorithm that I
implemented it's unlikely there's other
compaction algorithms that I plan that
would be more that would be better for
performance
I plan to implement those later but not
now okay well the thing is like so for a
very long time people kept saying that
writing a compactor for Ruby was or for
MRI was not possible like you just
couldn't do it but I figured out a way
to do it and the way that I do it is
independent of the actual compaction
algorithm hmm okay so what it means is I
just chose like the easiest compaction
algorithm because that's not really the
problem I was dream yeah yeah right I
was trying to solve like is this
actually possible right and then once we
figure out oh yeah it is possible we
could do this now I'll implement a more
like a more efficient and more
performance friendly technique what was
the specific part of Ruby that people
said like it couldn't be done so the
main issue is that is C extensions so
when you if you allocate like let's say
I
located an object in Ruby and I pass
that object to a C extension the C
extension gets the address of that
object and it's a direct address so if
that C extension were to save the
address somewhere and then the compactor
ran in that object up yeah and the
address is wrong right and the C side
would say quality yeah yes so the what I
did was essentially i piggybacked off of
the mark function so when you if you
have a C extension and you have a
reference to a ruby object
you're supposed to implement
mark-and-sweep functions and you're
supposed to mark that pointer so what I
did is I said okay any object that gets
marked we don't allow it to move okay so
internally Ruby uses a different marking
on marking function then C extensions
use Oh interesting so that was that was
also part of the work that I had to do
is say like okay what we're gonna do is
we're gonna take this this public API
that everybody uses yeah we'll ensure
that those objects do not move Ruby's
internal one we're gonna do something
completely different because we know
what to do will we can handle the
situation right right so that was the
that was essentially the technique I
came up with and after doing that what
it means is that certain portion certain
objects can't move but it also means
safety for your C extensions so that
means that when it comes to C extensions
does that mean there will always be like
holes I guess in terms of the compaction
no not necessarily because the the way
Ruby is GC works or the way it's
allocator works is that it allocates a
page it's essentially an arena and a
memory arena of each page is about 16 K
I think basically we allocate objects
out of that out of that arena and then
your heap is composed of multiple pages
so obviously you probably want your
program to use more than 16 K sure but
that's more than enough for anyone yes
so we have multiple pages but what I did
is I said the
I take those pages and the compactor
sorts them by the number of unmovable
objects they have okay so then we just
pack around all of those unmovable
objects okay
so even though we have some that can't
move we can still make sure that
everything yeah yeah interesting okay so
it seems to work well and then I also
introduced a compaction callback for C
extensions hmm
so let's say you have a C extension and
you want to support the compactor you
can register a callback that'll say like
every time the compactor runs york this
callback will be called and you have
your C extension has an opportunity to
update its update its own reference okay
so there's another function that you can
call and say hey here's a reference I
have is this right mm-hmm and then the
GC will tell you oh yes that's fine or
no it's actually now in this location
you need to update it so if you have
control over the C code then you can
actually you can say like I want to
allocate this memory and if you move it
let me know and then so my pointer will
still continue to point at the right
location even if it got there
yes awesome yeah yeah yeah so that's I
I'm excited about yeah and I'm learning
a lot too like yeah it's it's like when
you program in a high-level language
like you know Ruby or Python or even
Java like it's like you don't you don't
really think about what's happening
under the hood and yeah it's just it's
just awesome how much you know how much
goes into it yeah I think it's I think
it's really good though like you
shouldn't I think most programmers
shouldn't really have to think about
that type of stuff like really you just
want to be like you want to be writing
your app or whatever whatever problem is
you try to solve so I think it's
actually cool that we have abstractions
like that that you don't have to have to
bother yeah yeah awesome well I'm glad
you're on the case thank you is there
anything else that you want to mention
or not I can't think of anything else no
no I mean jits
super exciting just I think
Ruby's future is very bright mm-hmm so
on the heels of Ruby kegui seeing all
the awesome announcements at that
conference like I am really excited yeah
I mean it seems like and maybe it's a
not a correct perception but it seemed
like Ruby as a language it didn't seem
like there was a lot of big changes
happening at least from the outside and
then it seems like there are a ton of
things that are coming all at all at
once is that does that sorta so I think
so yeah that sounds it sounds truthy to
me I mean we don't like I don't think
there are huge like language level
changes but I think that the underlying
technology and the new developments and
like new libraries and smells that are
coming out it's just like I feel like
there is a new life I guess it's just
like I think right now is a very
exciting time very cool what are some
good resources for someone who wants to
learn more about the Ruby runtime or
learn more about the work you're doing
I would suggest a book called ruby under
a microscope that book is very good
about Ruby internals teaches like it
covers Ruby internals really well yeah
so I recommend I recommend that book for
the stuff I'm doing me in particular my
I really enjoy a book called GC handbook
I actually stole like all of my
someone's paper I write like I recommend
like if you're interested in GC like GC
topics I recommend that one
compiler books I don't know there's like
there's a lot of compiler books out
there I mean but the best one that's I
think the best book that's specific to
Ruby internals would be the
Ruby under a microscope for sure yeah I
had a chance to kind of go through it
and it's really it's really fantastic
yeah it's great it's great it's in-depth
its how old is that book now maybe three
years yeah I think I got reprinted or
something threw no starch maybe yeah
maybe 2014 I don't know it's so it's I
mean obviously like books age yeah but
it's like it's still I would say that
it's like very accurate still for sure
finally how can people follow you you
can follow me yeah
my nickname is tender love you can find
me on Twitter with that name and also I
might get hub with that name and also on
my Instagram with that name I don't have
a SoundCloud though but it's coming it's
coming yes don't forget to like follow
and subscribe absolutely all right
Aaron thank you so much for coming on
the show thank you so much it's been a
pleasure this is Jeremy Jung for
software engineering radio thank you for
listening thanks thanks for listening
the se radio an educational program
brought to you by out your police
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at SE - radio net to provide
feedback you can comment on each episode
on the website or reach us on LinkedIn
Facebook Twitter or through our slack
channel at SC radio.com you can also
email us at team @ SC - radio net this
and all other episodes of se radio is
licensed under Creative Commons license
2.5 thanks for listening